A Guide to the Carlisle Havelock Morrissett Papers, 1893-1976
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Carlisle Havelock Morrissett Papers, 1893-1976
The Library of Virginia
44057
4.5 cu. ft.
Carlisle Havelock Morrissett.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Carlisle Morrissett Branch, Richmond.
Biographical Information
Carlisle Havelock Morrissett was born in Richmond, Virginia on 25 January 1892. He was the son of William J. Morrissett and Hattie Augusta Nollner. Morrissett attended Piedmont Business College, and Washington and Lee University's law school, where he graduated in 1914. He also taught summer law school courses there for a short period. He practiced law privately in Lynchburg, and then became counsel and researcher for the committee to revise the Code of Virginia in 1919. Afterwards, Morrissett became director of the Legislative Reference Bureau. In 1921, he edited the second edition of "Pleading and Practice in Actions at Common Law" by Martin P. Burks. In 1923, he compiled and annotated the "General Laws of the Commonwealth of Virginia." Governor Harry F. Byrd appointed Morrissett the state's first tax commissioner, and he served in that post until his retirement in 1970. He was also a member of the Compensation Board, Treasury Board, Board of Trustees of the Virginia Supplemental Retirement System, and the State Commission on Local Debt. Morrissett married Gertrude M. Nance in May, 1920. He died in Richmond on 2 December 1976, and is buried in Hollywood Cemetery.
Scope and Content
Papers, 1893-1976, of Carlisle Havelock Morrissett (1892-1976) of Richmond, Virginia, relating to his work as director of the Legislative Reference Bureau, and as State Tax Commissioner, for the Commonwealth of Virginia. Includes articles, certificates, clippings, correspondence, drafts of legislation, law school exercises, notes, and examinations, opinions and research papers on various topics, publications, reports of state government agencies, drafts of revisions to the Code of Virginia, and speeches.
Topics covered in the correspondence include Morrissett's work with the Code Revision Committee in 1918-1919, and his exemption from military service during World War I so he could complete its work. Other subjects include Legislative Reference Bureau research inquiries, and his reappointments by various Virginia governors. There are letters between Morrissett and Harry Flood Byrd covering personal, campaign, tax, and other legislative issues. There is also a large amount of correspondence relating to Morrissett's retirement from state service in 1970.
Contents List
- Accounts and Receipts (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Act - "To Reorganize the Administration of State Government," 1927 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Address - "Extrinsic Evidence in Respect to Written Instruments" by Charles A. Graves, Virginia State Bar Association, 2 August 1893 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Address - "The Virginia Code of 1919" by Martin P. Burks, Judge of the Supreme Court of Appeals before the Virginia State Bar Association, Richmond, Virginia, 15-17 May 1919 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Address - "Virginia Statutes of 1924" by C.H. Morrissett before the Virginia State Bar Association, Winchester, 3 July 1924 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Address - "Legal Aspects of Virginia Juvenile and Domestic Relations Court" by C.H. Morrissett before the Summer Institute of Public Welfare, University of Virginia, 21-27 August 1924 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Address - To the Commissioners of Revenue by C.H. Morrissett, Delivered in 1926, at Roanoke, Bristol, Danville, Norfolk, Harrisonburg, Fredericksburg, and Richmond (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Address - "Looking Forward - An Address on Governmental Reorganization and the Future Outlook for Virginia" by Gov. Harry Flood Byrd, Farmers 4H Club of Madison County, 15 July 1927 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Address - "Virginia's Business Government" by Gov. Harry Flood Byrd, before the General Assembly of Virginia, 11 January 1928 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Address - "Program of Progress" by Gov. Harry Flood Byrd, delivered before the General Assembly of Virginia, 16 January 1928 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Address - "Virginia Statutes of 1928" by C.H. Morrissett before the Virginia State Bar Association at Old Point Comfort, Virginia, 2 August 1928 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Address - "Virginia Statutes of 1930" by C.H. Morrissett before the Virginia State Bar Association at Old Point Comfort, Virginia, 8 August 1930 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Article - Morrissett, C.H. "The Improvement of Local Taxation in Relation to the State." Virginia Municipal Review, vol. XVII, no. 12 (December 1940) (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Article - Morrissett, C.H. "Taxation of State Food Merchants with a Note on Unfair Sales Act." The Virginia Foodman, vol. XIV, no. 4 (April 1953) (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Article - Morrissett, C.H. "Virginia's General Fund: Major Developments" The University of Virginia Newsletter, vol. XXXV, no. 6 (December 15, 1958) (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Article - Morrissett, C. H. "Capital Not Otherwise Taxed in Virginia." The Virginia Accountant, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Bill - "Concerning taxation - to segregate for the purposes of taxation, the several kinds or classes of property..." Senate Bill No. 71 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Biographical Information (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Brief - Eppa Hunton IV v. Commonwealth of Virginia, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Broadside (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Certificates (see also "Oversize") (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Children's Code Commission, 1921-1922 - History (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Clippings, 1924-1929 (Box 2, Folder 1-3)
- Clippings, 1930-1939 (Box 2, Folder 4-6)
- Clippings, 1940-1949 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Clippings, 1950-1959 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Clippings, 1960-1969 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Clippings, 1970-1975 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Correspondence, 1913-1916 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1917 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1918 (January-April) (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 1918 (May-December) (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1919 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 1920-1929 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 1930-1939 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Correspondence, 1940-1949 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Correspondence, 1957-1958 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Correspondence, 1960-1969 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Correspondence, 1970-1976 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Declarations of Estimated Income Tax by Corporations and Payment of Estimated Income Tax (Box 4, Folder 1-3)
- Editorial - "How High Virginia's Taxes?" - Newport News Times-Herald, 19 February 1951 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Editorial - "Morrissett's Epigram" - Lynchburg News, 1 September 1955 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- "The Effects of the Federal Estate Tax Credit on State Finances" (Box 4, Folder 6)
- House Bill 100 Paste-Up, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 7-9)
- Law School Course Examinations, 1911-1916 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Law School Exercises, Notes, Materials, etc. (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Legislative Bills, 1928 (Box 4, Folder 12-14)
- Minutes - Judicial Council of Virginia, 1 August 1929 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Miscellaneous (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Opinions, etc. - Book 1, 1919-1921 (Box 5, Folder 3-5)
- Opinions, etc. - Book 2, 1921 (Box 5, Folder 6-7)
- Opinions, etc. - Book 3, 1921-1922 (Box 5, Folder 8-10)
- Opinions, etc. - Book 4, 1922-1924 (Box 5, Folder 11-12)
- Opinions, etc. - Book 4, 1922-1924 (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Opinions, etc. - Book 5, 1924 (Box 6, Folder 2-3)
- Opinions, etc., 1924-1925 (Box 6, Folder 4-5)
- Opinions, etc., 1925-1926 (Box 6, Folder 6-8)
- Oversize - Photographs and Certificates (Map-case 2, Drawer 13)
- Photographs (see also "Oversize") (Box 6, Folder 9)
- "Pleading and Practice in Actions at Common Law" by Martin P. Burks (2nd Edition), 1921 (Box 6, Folder 10)
- "Progress the Keynote of the Byrd Administration" (Box 6, Folder 11)
- Publication - "Notes of Lectures on the Law of Wills and Administration" by Joseph R. Long, 1910 (Box 6, Folder 12)
- Publication - "Questions of Real Property." Prepared for the Students of Washington and Lee University by Abram P. Staples, 1916? (Box 6, Folder 12)
- Publication - "The Education and Economic Development of the Negro in Virginia" by W.H. Brown. Publications of the University of Virginia Phelps-Stokes Fellowship Papers, Number Six, 1923 (Box 6, Folder 12)
- Publication - "The Negroes of Lynchburg, Virginia" by Benjamin Guy Childs, 1923 (Box 6, Folder 12)
- Publication - "Taxation in Virginia" by William H. Stauffer (NewYork: The Century Co.), Forward by C.H. Morrissett, 1931 (Box 6, Folder 12)
- Publication - "Shall I Become a Lawyer?" by James Grafton Rogers, Assistant Secretary of State, University of Chicago Press, 1933 (Box 6, Folder 12)
- Publication - "Conflict of Laws - Cases and Materials (Sixth Edition)." Willis L.M. Reese and Maurice Rosenberg. 1973 Supplement (Box 6, Folder 12)
- Report - "Juvenile and Welfare Laws as Amended by the General Assembly of Virginia," 1922 (Box 7)
- Report - "Virginia Election Laws in Effect June 16, 1924." Issued by B.O. James, Secretary of the Commonwealth (Box 7)
- Report - "Virginia - Layman Prohibition Law in Effect June 16, 1924." (Box 7)
- Report - "Circular to Commissioners of Revenue on Their Powers and Duties Respecting the Assessment of Taxes on Persons, Personal Property, Money, Incomes, and Real Estate." Issued by the Auditor of Public Accounts, 2 February 1925 (Box 7)
- Report - "Statistics with Reference to the Plan of Segregation - Proposed in Senate Bill No. 179," 1926 (Box 7)
- Report - "Annual Report of the Auditor of Public Accounts to the Governor of Virginia for the Fiscal Year Ending June 30, 1927." (Box 7)
- Report - "Organization and Management of the State Government of Virginia - Report on the Survey made for the Governor and his Committee on Consolidation and Simplification," 1927 (Box 7)
- Report - "Proposed Amendments to the Constitution of Virginia" - Agreed to by the General Assembly of Virginia at the Regular Session of 1926 and the Extra Session of 1927 (Box 7)
- Report - "Report of the Citizens Committee on Consolidation and Simplification in State and Local Governments," 1927 (Box 7)
- Report - "Report on the Taxation of Public Service Corporations in Virginia" by C.H. Morrissett, February 10, 1928 (Senate Doc. No. 9) (Box 7)
- Report - "Virginia Tax Laws - Report of the Commission to Revise, Collate, Simplify and Codify the General Tax Laws of Virginia," 1928 (Senate Doc. No. 7) (Box 7)
- Report - "Report of Comptroller to the Governor of Virginia for Appropriation Year Ended February 28, 1929." (Box 7)
- Report - "Report of the Department of Taxation to the Governor of Virginia for the Period Beginning April 15, 1926, and Ending June 29, 1929." (Box 7)
- Report - "Report of the Department of Taxation to the Governor of Virginia for the Fiscal Year Ending June 30, 1930" (Box 7)
- Report - "Report of the Judicial Council of Virginia to the Governor and Supreme Court of Appeals," 1930 (Box 7)
- Report - "Report of Comptroller to the Governor of Virginia for Fiscal Year Ended June 30, 1931." (Box 7)
- Report - "Report of the Department of Taxation to the Governor of Virginia for the Fiscal Year Ending June 30, 1931." (Box 7)
- Report - "Report of the Department of Taxation to the Governor of Virginia for the Fiscal Year Ending June 30, 1932" (Box 7)
- Report - "Report of the Commission to Study the Forestry Conditions of Virginia to the General Assembly," 1932 (Box 7)
- Report - "Taxes on Real Estate - Report (Majority and Minority) of the Committee to Study the Burden of Taxes on Real Estate," 1932 (House Doc. No. 7) (Box 7)
- Report - "Report of the Department of Taxation to the Governor of Virginia for the Fiscal Year Ending June 30, 1933." (Box 7)
- Report - "Report of the Department of Taxation to the Governor of Virginia for the Fiscal Year Ending June 30, 1934." (Box 7)
- Report - "Report of the Department of Taxation to the Governor of Virginia for the Fiscal Year Ending June 30, 1935." (Box 7)
- Report - "Locally Taxable Values in Virginia," 1943 (Box 7)
- Report - "Report of the Department of Taxation to the Governor of Virginia for the Fiscal Year Ending June 30, 1947." (Box 7)
- Report - "State and Local Taxation." Report of the Commission to Study Sate and Local Taxation to the Governor and the General Assembly of Virginia, 1947 (Box 7)
- Report - "Taxation of Public Service Corporations in Virginia," Public Service Tax Study Committee, 1947 (Box 7)
- Report - "State and Local Revenues and Expenditures,' 1949 (Box 7)
- Report - "Report of Comptroller to the Governor of Virginia for Fiscal Year Ended June 30, 1952." (Box 7)
- Report - "Report of the Commission on State and Local Revenues and Expenditures and Related Matters to the Governor and the General Assembly of Virginia," 1963 (Box 7)
- Report - "Report of Comptroller to the Governor of Virginia for Fiscal Year Ended June 30, 1968." (Box 7)
- Report - "Report of the Comptroller to the Governor of Virginia for Fiscal Year Ended June 30, 1970" (Box 7)
- Retirement, 1969 (September) (Box 8, Folder 1)
- Retirement, 1969 (October 1-7) (Box 8, Folder 2)
- Retirement, 1969 (October 8-14) (Box 8, Folder 3)
- Retirement, 1969 (October 15-20) (Box 8, Folder 4)
- Retirement, 1969 (October 21-31) (Box 8, Folder 5)
- Retirement, 1969 (November) (Box 8, Folder 6)
- Retirement, 1969 (December) (Box 8, Folder 7)
- Retirement, 1970 (January 1-15) (Box 8, Folder 8)
- Retirement, 1970 (January 16-31) (Box 8, Folder 9)
- Retirement, 1970 (February) (Box 8, Folder 10)
- Retirement, 1970 (March-April) (Box 8, Folder 11)
- Retirement - Miscellaneous (Box 8, Folder 12)
- Revisions to the Virginia Code, 1918 (Box 8, Folder 13-16)
- Revisions to the Virginia Code, 1918 (Box 9, Folder 1)
- Speech - "Virginia Statutes of 1924," Virginia State Bar Association, Winchester, 3 July 1924 (Box 9, Folder 2)
- Speech - "Joint Guardianship Bill," Richmond League of Women Voters, 7 December 1925 (Box 9, Folder 3)
- Speech - Civitan Club, Richmond, 8 January 1926 (Box 9, Folder 4)
- Speech - League of Virginia Municipalities, Farmville, 6 October 1926 (Box 9, Folder 5)
- Speech - "Virginia is Ready" by Gov. John Garland Pollard (Prepared by CHM), 1930 (Box 9, Folder 6)
- Speech - "How Much Should the Drinker Pay?" (Radio Address), 1935 (Box 9, Folder 7)
- Speech - "The Constitution of the United States of America," Williamsburg, 17 September 1946 (Box 9, Folder 8)
- Speech - WRNL Interview, 21 April 1949 (Box 9, Folder 9)
- Speech - WRNL Interview, 12 April 1950 (Box 9, Folder 10)
- Speech - WRNL Interview, 321 April 1952 (Box 9, Folder 11)
- Speech - "Inter-Governmental Relations," 23 July 1953 (Box 9, Folder 12)
- Speech - Local Government Officials' Conference, Commissioners of the Revenue Section, University of Virginia, 1 September 1953 (Box 9, Folder 13)
- Speech - "Federal-State Relationships Affected by the Internal Revenue Code," Williamsburg, 25 September 1954 (Box 9, Folder 14)
- Speech - "The State Tax Commission and Your Municipality," Richmond, 25 September 1956 (Box 9, Folder 15)
- Speech - Commonwealth Club, 10 April 1957 (Box 9, Folder 16)
- Speech - "The Tax Situation," 22 April 1958 (Box 9, Folder 17)
- Speech - Kiwanis Club Introduction, 19 October 1959 (Box 9, Folder 18)
- Speech - Virginia Association of Assessing Officers, Virginia Beach, 2 September 1960 (Box 9, Folder 19)
- Speech - Norfolk Television Interview, 13 April 1962 (Box 9, Folder 20)
- Speech - Richmond and Sandston Rotary Club, 16 April and 13 May 1963 (Box 9, Folder 21)
- Speech - TV/Radio Press Conference, 27 April 1963 (Box 9, Folder 22)
- Speech - Department of Taxation Recognition and Orientation Program, 25 July 1975 (Box 9, Folder 23)
- Speech - Constitution Day (Various Dates) (Box 9, Folder 24)
- Speech - "Fee Officers," n.d. (Box 9, Folder 25)
- Speech - "The Greatness of Washington," n.d. (Box 9, Folder 26)
- Speech - International Association of Milk Control Agencies, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 27)
- Speech - Legal Club of Lynchburg, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 28)
- Speech - "Maryland Speech," n.d. (Box 9, Folder 29)
- Speech - Norfolk and Portsmouth Bar Association, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 30)
- Speech - "Present Day Tax Problems in Virginia," n.d. (Box 9, Folder 31)
- Speech - "Segregation of the Subjects of Taxation," n.d. (Box 9, Folder 32)
- Speech - "Suggested Amendments to the Constitution of Virginia" by Gov. Stuart (Prepared by CHM), n.d. (Box 9, Folder 33)
- Speech - "The Tax Situation in Virginia," Virginia Real Estate Association, Winchester, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 34)
- Speech - "Ten Minute Talk on Taxes," n.d. (Box 9, Folder 35)
- Speech - Virginia League of Municipalities, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 36)
- Speech - Virginia Manufacturers Association, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 37)
- Speech - Virginia Society of Public Accountants, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 38)
- Speech - "Women and the Law," n.d. (Box 9, Folder 39)
- Speeches - Miscellaneous (Box 9, Folder 40)
- Statement - "Repeal of the State Tax on Land and Personal Property" by Gov. Harry F. Byrd on the repeal of the 25 cent State Tax on Land and Personal Property, showing the effect on each locality, and based on actual and not estimated returns, 1927 (Box 10, Folder 1)
- Statement - "Proposed Amendments to the Constitution of Virginia" by C.H. Morrissett, 1927 (Box 10, Folder 1)
- Statement - "The Tax Situation in Virginia - A Statement Showing the Effect of New Tax Laws" by Gov. Harry Flood Byrd, 1927 (Box 10, Folder 1)
- Statement - "General Assembly Was Right on Beer," 1935 (Box 10, Folder 1)
- Statement - "Proposal to Allow Federal Income Taxes to be Deducted from Gross Income in Preparing Virginia Income Tax Returns," 11 February 1950 (Box 10, Folder 1)
- Statement - C. H. Morrissett, State Tax Commissioner of Virginia, before Sub-committee No.2 of the Committee on the Judiciary, U.S. House of Representatives, at a hearing on April 29, 1959, on proposed constitutional amendments designed to impair the jurisdiction of the States to tax the incomes of non-residents; also bills on certain Senate compacts (Box 10, Folder 2)
- Statement - "State Income Tax Witholding and Declarations of Estimated Income Tax," 8 April 1962 (Box 10, Folder 2)
- Statement - "Taxation," 1963 (Box 10, Folder 2)
- Statement - "Washington-Maryland-Virginia Complex: State and District Individual Income Taxation," 12 March 1963 (Box 10, Folder 2)
- Statement - H.R. 11798, 15 April 1966 (Box 10, Folder 2)
- Statement - Dissenting Statement by C.H. Morrissett and George D. Fischer, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 2)
- Surber-Arundale Company (Publishers) (Box 10, Folder 3)
- "There is No End" by R. Dean Goodwin (Review) (Box 10, Folder 4)
- Virginia Retail Sales and Use Tax Act, 1966 (Box 10, Folder 5-10)